A Guide to the Papers of Sandra McDonald, American Rhododendron Society 1973-2002
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Sandra McDonald, American Rhododendron Society 1973-2002
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10553-bb
5 Hollinger boxes, 2 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Special Collections Library by Sandra F. McDonald, August 28, 2004.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of Sandra McDonald's personal rhododendron papers and correspondence with other rhododendron fanciers and friends and her position as president of the Mid-Atlantic Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society, ca. 500 items (5 Hollinger boxes, 2 linear feet), 1973-2002. The papers contain correspondence files, including one for The Azalean; McDonald's presidential proposal, Breeder's Roundtable papers; clippings; and newsletters (the newsletters were transferred to Rare Books). In addition the papers contain papers from the American Rhododendron Society Research Committee, Long Range Planning Committee, Editorial Search Committee and Smith Garden Committee.
Arrangement
These papers are arranged alphabetically by folder heading within three series, Series I: Correspondence; Series II: Topical Files - General; and Series III: Topical Files - American Rhododendron Society; then alphabetically by correspondent name within the correspondence folders and chronologically within the other folders.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence - A-B, correspondents include: Richard C. Aldridge, Jr., Frank Arsen, Reid Bahnson, Peter Barber, Mr. and Mrs. Albert Behnke, Barbara and Walter Bell, Esther Berry, Ivo Benes, Mr. and Mrs. Richard H. Birkett, James Bowyer, William P. Bradley, George Brubaker, Ray Brush, John B. Buschmann, and Max E. Byrkit1952-2002 (Box-folder 1:1)
    arranged alphabetically by correspondent
  - Correspondence - The Azalean, correspondents include: Page Calisch, Charles H. Evans, and Robert W. Hobbs. Also present is an article “Azaleas for Commercial Forcing,” and a membership list1983-1989 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence - Michael Breiding1985-1992 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence - Dick Brooks1994-1997 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence - C, correspondents include: Allen Cantrell, Richard, W. Chaikin, Mr. and Lorraine Chappell, Malcolm Clark, Joe Coleman, Ed Collins, Harold Crutcher, and Merl [Cuthen?]1984-1996 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence - D-F, correspondents include: Stephen Dalton (picture of a rhododendron leaf hopper only), Weldon Delp, Henry Dobbs, Ian Donovan, George F. Drake, Phil Duryee, William Eckman, Jeanne Edwards, Newton Edwards, Larry Englander, Bruno Falanga, Bill Fetterhoff, Art Frazer, and Bob Furman1978-1989 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence - G-H, correspondents include: Russell Gilkey, Helen Hahn, Fred R. Hamilton, Jeanne M. Hammer, Klaus Hansen, Pamela J. Harper, Henritta Hass, Mavis Haywood, Dr. and Mrs. Herbert Hechenbleikner, David Hinton, Paul Holschuh, Heman A. Howard, and Don Hyatt1975-2002 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence - Fred and Betty Galle Newspaper Clipping1982-1999 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence - Herman Gehnrich List of Hybrids1992 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence - Barbara Hall1988-1996 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence - J-L, correspondents include: Bruno Kaelin, Don Kellam, Fritz Kempf, Dr. Kumar, Dr. G. David Lewis, and Fleur L. Long1982-1989 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence - Adele Jones (ARS Quarterly Journal Editor)1987 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence - Joe Jones (ARS Treasurer)1988 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Correspondence - August Kehr, concerning 1988 Breeders Roundtable1987-1988 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Correspondence and Papers Related to Austin Kennell, Obituary1982-2002 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Correspondence and Papers Related to Robert Lambe1973-1984 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Correspondence - David Lay1984-1993 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Correspondence - M, correspondents include: Bruce Macdonald, Nina Mann, Dr. William M. Massie, Roy D. Milne, and Dr. Robert Munger1980-1996 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Correspondence - Ken McDonald with Other Middle Atlantic Chapter Members, correspondents include: R. E. Baldwin, Johnson M. Colemon, August Kehr, Mavis Haywood, R. C. Lambe, R. S. Lindstrom Harry Nash, Bill Stepka ,E.L. Rowell, and Thomas F. Wheeldon1974-1977 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Correspondence - George McLellan, includes ARS brochure1987-1993 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Correspondence - Harry Nash 1975 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Correspondence - P-S, correspondents include: Harold Pilkington, George Ring, Martha K. Roane, H. E. Salley, Peter B. Schultz, Jonathan A. Shaw, Myron Shear, Terry Sheuchenko, A. W. Smith, David Smith, Ted Stevenson, Eric Streater, Eleanor Stubbs, and Dorothy Swift 1977-1995 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Correspondence - Frank Pelurie2001-2002 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Correspondence - H. Edward Reiley1990-1992 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence - Dorothy Robinson, Middle Atlantic Chapter Secretary1987-1991 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Correspondence - Dorothy Robinson1991-1997 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Correspondence - Yukio Sasaki and Hideo Suzuki1980-1991 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence - Ted Scott1988-1990 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Correspondence and Papers Related to-Bill Stepka1978-2001 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence - Kendon Stubbs1986-1988 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Correspondence - T-Z, correspondents include: Dr. Robert Ticknor, Kenneth C. Torres, John Weagh, Dr. Franklin West, Gladys Wheeldon, Margaret K. White, Frank F. Willingham, Jr., Joan Winter, Kelly Wise, Harry Wise, D. D. Withers, Douglas M. Wood, Geoffrey and Karen Woodward, J.S. Yeates, and Mathias C. Zack1975-1994 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Correspondence - Lynn Watts1999-2000 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Topical Files - General
  - Breeder's Roundtable1986-1988 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Breeder's Roundtable Transcripts and Corrections1988 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - California Chapter1976-1978 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Austin Kennell - Gold Medal Correspondence1991-1997 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Membership Cards of Kenneth and Sandra McDonald1973-1976 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Members, Papers Concerning1981-1997 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Presidency of Sandra McDonald, Proposals and Related Activities1987-1989 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Projects - Disease Questionnaire1987-1988 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Projects - Flower Shows1977-1995 (Box-folder 3:2))
  - Middle Atlantic Chapter Projects - Heat Tolerance Study1984 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - National Convention - Middle Atlantic Chapter1987 Oct-1988 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - National Convention - Middle Atlantic Chapter1987 Jan -1987 Sep (Box-folder 3:5)
  - National Convention - Middle Atlantic Chapter1980- 1986 Dec (Box-folder 3:6)
  - National Convention - Flower Show1982-1988 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - National Convention - Speakers1986-1988 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - The Potomac Valley Chapter1974-1982 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Rhododendron Society of Canada1975-1978 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Rhododendron Species Foundation - Plant Distribution Lists1976-1981 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Southeastern Chapter1976-1980 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Tidewater Chapter1974-1976 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Vancouver Chapter1975-1978 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Virginia Garden - Boxerwood by Robert S. and Elizabeth E. Munger1978 Dec (Box-folder 4:5)
- Topical Files - American Rhododendron Society
  - ARS - The Cecil and Molly Smith Garden Committee1985-1987 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - ARS - Editorial Committee1994-1999 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - ARS - Editorial Committee1993 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - ARS - Editorial Committee1990 Jul-1992 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - ARS - Editorial Committee1987-1990 Jun (Box-folder 4:10)
  - ARS - Editorial Committee1983-1986 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - ARS - Editorial Search Committee1990 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - ARS - Long Range Planning Committee1984-1993 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - ARS - Publication "The Fundamentals of Rhododendron and Azalea Culture" by Sandra McDonald1982-1990 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - ARS - Research Committee1986 May -1995 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - ARS - Research Committee1983 Oct- 1986 Apr (Box-folder 5:6)
  - ARS - Research Committee1976- 1983 Sep (Box-folder 5:7)